Hi everyone I'm Nils and I will present you our Late-Breaking work about implementing
the theory of constructed emotion utilizing large
language models. Current emotion classification is
often very simplistic and puts human emotions
into a set of discrete categories like anger
happiness or sadness it totally neglects the
recent advancements in cognitive and emotional
studies. We demonstrate witin a practical use case
in online content moderation how to use LLMs for
differentiated and context sensitive emotion
analysis. We start this by first building the
context sphere where we include all the relevant
information available of a single user. We include
not only single comments of a user but also
surrounding context this includes the full
comment history, threats, metadata and article data.
But part of the context sphere is also to exclude
context which is not relevant to the user. Then
the large language model comes into play since
we want to use the Theory of Constructed Emotion
by Lisa Feldmann Barett, we ask ourselfs, who could apply
this Theory better than herself. We let
the LLM impersonate Lisa Feldmann Barett and
use controlled generation to guide her response. Both
methods are techniques to guide LLMs making
it reproducible and generalizable. The output is
evaluated using an LLM-as-a-Judge approach where
four different LLMs check for confabulations also
known as hallucinations meaning content which is
misleading but confident. If confabulations are
detected the pipeline will stop processing, if
it is successful the pipeline will produce an
output as shown in the results. We can show that
the LLM successfully analyzes emotions considering
individual user context, capturing nuanced emotional
dynamics going beyond traditional categorical
approaches. This work offers one approach which
shows that psychology and informatics can move
forward analyzing emotions not only with simple
categories but considering context and nuances in
emotions. We acknowledge that our current evaluation
using LLM-as-a-Judge approach is pragmatic but
lacks human validation. We also want to point out
that dynamic emotions lack a definitive ground
truth making it hard to Benchmark. Finally I'd
like to thank my colleagues Irina and Julia who
conducted this research with me, and I'd like
to thank the Christian Dobler Lab for Recommender Systems
at TU Wien. Thank you for your attention.